Guide to the James William Hook Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James William Hook papers
1919-1953
MS 288
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21.5
Eighty-four letter books covering the professional career of James William Hook, who was president and treasurer of Geometric Tool Company of New Haven, 1923-1944; member of President Hoover's National Organization on Unemployment Relief, 1931-1933; president of the New England Council; and president and director of United Illuminating Company, 1939-1942. There are letterbooks labeled general, Geometric Tool Company, National Association of Manufacturers, New England Council, unemployment activities, University of Connecticut, and United Illuminating Company. The collection also includes press clippings and genealogical information.
Hook, James W. (James William), 1884-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. J. W. Hook, 1958 and 1962.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence Files. II. Press Clippings and Genealogy.
Biographical / Historical
James W. Hook (1884-1957): engineer for Globe Machinery & Supply Co., Des Moines (1908-1909); manager of C.A. Durham Co., Marshalltown, Ia. (1909-1916); president and director of Allied Machinery Co. of America, New York (1916-1923); president and treasurer of Geometric Tool Co., New Haven, Ct. (1923-1944); president of United Illuminating Co. of New Haven (1939-1942); active on various boards and commissions.
Scope and Contents
Eighty-four letter books covering the professional career of James William Hook, who was president and treasurer of Geometric Tool Company of New Haven, 1923-1944; member of President Hoover's National Organization on Unemployment Relief, 1931-1933; president of the New England Council; and president and director of United Illuminating Company, 1939-1942. There are letterbooks labeled general, Geometric Tool Company, National Association of Manufacturers, New England Council, unemployment activities, University of Connecticut, and United Illuminating Company. The collection also includes press clippings and genealogical information.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Business; Depressions -- 1929 -- United States; Unemployed -- Connecticut; Unemployed -- United States; New Haven (Conn.); Businessmen; Engineers; Hook, James W. (James William), 1884-1957; Hook family; Geometric Tool Company (New Haven, Conn.); National Association of Manufacturers (U.S.); New England Council; United Illuminating Company (New Haven, Conn.); University of Connecticut
- Correspondence Files, Series I
  - General
    - Volume I, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Volume II, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - A-L, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - M-Y, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A-K, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - L-Y, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - A-K, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - L-Z, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A-J, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - K-Z, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - A-L, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - M-Z, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - A-L, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - M-Z, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - A-L, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - M-Z, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - A-M, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - N-Z, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - A-Z, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - A-Z, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - A-K, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - L-Z, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - A-L, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - M-Z, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - A-H, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - I-Z, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - A-K, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - L-Z, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - A-M, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - N-Z, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - A-L, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - M-Z, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 32)
    - A-K, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 33)
    - L-Z, 1944 (Box 20, Folder 34)
    - A-I, 1945 (Box 21, Folder 35)
    - J-Z, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 36)
    - A-K, 1946 (Box 23, Folder 37)
    - L-Y, 1946 (Box 23, Folder 38)
    - A-Z, 1947 (Box 24, Folder 39)
    - A-Z, 1948 (Box 25, Folder 40)
    - A-G, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 41)
    - H-Z, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - A-M, 1950 (Box 27, Folder 43)
    - N-Z, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 44)
  - Topical
    - Allied Machine Company
      - 1919-1920 (Box 29, Folder 45-58)
      - January 1921-April 1922 (Box 30, Folder 59-72)
      - 1922 (Box 31, Folder 73-86)
    - Durable Goods Committee
      - A-Z, 1934 (Box 32, Folder 87)
    - Geometric Tool Company
      - A-Z, 1939 (Box 33, Folder 88)
      - A-Z, 1940 (Box 34, Folder 89)
      - A-Z, 1941 (Box 35, Folder 90)
      - A-M, 1942 (Box 36, Folder 91)
    - United Illuminating Company
      General
      See also: boxes 44-45
      - A-Z, 1942 (Box 36, Folder 91)
    - Geometric Tool Company
      - N-Z, 1942 (Box 37, Folder 92)
    - United Illuminating Company
      General note
      - A-Z, 1942 (Box 37, Folder 92)
    - National Associations of Manufactures
      - A-Z, 1934 (Box 38, Folder 93)
      - A-Z, 1936 (Box 39, Folder 94)
    - New England Council
      See also: boxes 40-41
      - A-Z, 1936 (Box 39, Folder 94)
    - National Recovery Association
      - A-Z, 1933 (Box 39, Folder 95)
    - New England Council
      See also: box 39
      - A-Z, 1938 (Box 40, Folder 96)
      - A-Z, 1938 (Box 41, Folder 97)
    - Unemployment Activities
      - 1931-1932 (Box 42, Folder 98-99)
      - 1933 (Box 43, Folder 100)
    - United Illuminating Company
      See also: boxes 36-37
      - A-Z, 1939 (Box 44, Folder 101)
      - A-Z, 1940-41 (Box 45, Folder 102-103)
    - University of Connecticut
      - 1949-1950 (Box 46, Folder 104-105)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 47, Folder 106-107)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 48, Folder 108)
- Press Clippings and Genealogy, Series II
  - Press Clippings
    - 1929-1930 (Box 49, Folder 109)
    - 1931-1932 January (Box 50, Folder 110)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 51, Folder 111-12)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 52, Folder 113-14)
    - 1936, 1938 (Box 53, Folder 115-16)
    - 1938 (Box 54, Folder 117)
    - 1939-1946 (Box 55, Folder 118)
  - Genealogy
    - Arnold family, 1952 (Box 55, Folder 119)
    - Tyron, Jones, Harris, Lay Families, 1952 (Box 55, Folder 120)